You want to see how we do 3D animation in computer science or you want to be able to read this formula?
Hi, I'm Jerome and today we'll be looking at animation data
First thing first when we want to animate
we will usually start from a skeleton and a skeleton is a hierarchy of
Transform meaning that if I move one of my bone, I will have all these children move with it in
In computer science, when we have a hierarchy, usually we represent this as a tree and so
I have here the tree that represents my skeleton with the hips, spine, arms and so on.
I can give an index at each of those transforms and I will go depth first, so I will go from
0 to 7 in the order of my tree now.
And because I have all those index, I can easily find the parent of each transform.
Now to speed things up, usually what we do is that we transform that tree into an array
and I will have an array of transform and in my case here would be an array of matrix
4.4 so I can encode translation, rotation and scale directly in each of those matrix.
And then we also have the list of the parents that we computed before.
So we have a list of all the transform and list of all the parents.
We have all the information that was important for the skeleton itself.
If we want to make a pose, we need to parametrize the pose with the minimum needed informations.
And in this case, if I give the position of my root and the rotation of every bone, I
can pose my character in every pose in any way in the world.
So P0, I mean the position of the first bone,
and all the Qs represent the rotation Q,
because we will be more likely using quaternions.
If I want to do a motion out of this,
a motion is a function of time that
is parametrized with the same information.
But each parameter now need to be also a function of time.
So now I have a motion that can change through time.
And that's usually the formula we'll see in all the papers.
Because I will be using the Ubisoft LaForge Animation
Database, so the LaFan1.
They encode the data in the motion a bit differently.
And so what they do is that they decide that a motion is
parametrized by two tensors, one for the position and one for the quaternions, and each of those tensors
are basically all the positions through times for every bones and all the quaternions through
time for every bones. If we look into the tensor for the positions for instance, what we see is that
is a NumPy array that has a discrete time that has 30 frames per second and so you will have
a bunch of rows, one row per frame and then for each of those rows you will have a column
for all the bones. So you will get one frame with all the bones, all the position for every
bones and now because all those positions are actually 3d vectors basically all the positions
will be xyz and then you get a 3d vector that has number of frame number of bones xyz for the
position and that would be the same for the quaternion. So in our case the tensor for the
position is frame count bone count 3 and the tensor for the quaternion is frame count bone count
four because you get the w coming from the cotonium also.
So let's see how we can import this inside of NumPy. What I have is a framework that is
built on top of iPy widget that's allowed me to directly draw a 3D inside of my NumPy.
And I will load my character and I will display this character so you can see
what we have here. So the structure of the skeleton, as I said, you get the root. Well,
I get the root here on the ground and I get all my root, all my transform. So they're
each time you transform and you get the link between them. So that's my skeleton for my character.
And if I load one animation, for instance, you could see how the framework gives us this
distances, so for the positions I get 7,000 frames, 22 bones and XYZ and quaternions 7,000 frames,
22 bones and XYZW for the quaternion. And if I want to render this animation, I can see this
animation. The particularity of the Lafan is that they've given the transform for every bone
inside of the animation directly so you could see that my character now is a
bit deformed compared to what the LaFan animation has and that's because I've
applied the transform coming from the animation onto my skeleton so I've
basically changed the shape of my skeleton. What I will want to do is to
make sure that I will match the bone translate from my skeleton and for this
I will reload the animation but giving it the character I want to use in my case and now I will
actually have the the same animation except that is mapped onto my character so the rotation comes
from the the from the from the tensors and I've replaced most of the translate with the
translate of my skeleton except for the root you could see that my character doesn't have the same
shape, doesn't have the same size. So what happened is that I have my feet on the ground
in this case, but that's not too worry. And one other thing that we have is that my skeleton has
a root on top of the hips, except that the Lafan one starts from the hips directly. So my animation
has start from the hips and you see that my roots stays there in 000. When we are in video game,
Usually what we do is is to use that route to represent where the character would be
inside of the world. So we don't start the animation at the hips itself. Usually we have a
route on the ground and that route represents the entity itself, represents the capsule for the physics
where you collide and that kind of stuff. So we tend to have a route that stays
under the character as close as possible. So what I would do is that I would start from the
animation here from the Lafane and I will compute automatically a route that goes under
the hips of my character. The way I'm doing this is basically taking the position of the hips
and I project it on the ground and I take the forward axis of the hips but I have here so
get my forward axis here and I will also project the rotation on the ground so I project the axis
I compute the angle around. So I don't have something that rotates in any direction on the
ground. I'll only rotate to have the forward axis of the character basically on the ground
and I get the projection. And so I project the hips and then because I will be moving the root,
it will actually also move the hips. So I need to compute the inverse matrix to bring this back
at the same spot. And that's what is computed here. So projecting on the ground and bringing back
the hips and the root and what you have then is this. So now we have the same animation as before
except that you could see my root is right under my hips, rotated with my hips. So it gives me
an indication of why the forward is and that kind of stuff. And the advantage of having a root like
this is basically now I could decide if I want to play the animation on that root or not,
and I could say, stay here, stay here in 0, 0, 0. And that's how you have the animation on spot.
If you actually want to have the animation on spot for some reason, you could also say that you
you want to turn off the rotation and you have it completely on spot as local motion relative to
a root motion that now is completely turned on and off. So you could turn on and off just the
root keeping a bunch of the motion and that kind of stuff. That's the advantage of having a root at
the bottom. What you could see as I said before is that my character doesn't have the same proportion
as the character from the Laffman one, so I have my foot that are on the ground
and also they are sliding if I bring back my character, where are you?
The feet position will not be static on the ground, they start to slide a bit and all that kind
of stuff and that would lead us to the study of our first paper in the next video. So I hope you
enjoyed this one and if you want you could subscribe so you can know when I
will start to publish the next videos studying those papers. See you next time.